Finding Aid for Secretary (University of Michigan) Records 1845-1953 (bulk 1908-1944)
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
Secretary (University of Michigan) records 1845-1953, 1908-1944
University of Michigan. Secretary.
9 linear feet
Correspondence and other files of University of Michigan Secretary Shirley W. Smith and of Controller and Assistant Secretary John C. Christensen. The files document university operations, relations with the state legislature, business and financial matters, buildings and grounds, and such university events as the graduation commencement. The files also relate to the university's struggles during the Depression to maintain its facilities and to provide employment for deserving students as seen in its relations with the Federal Emergency Relief Administration and the National Youth Administration. There are also earlier collected files of treasurers George S. Baker and James H. Wade.
87300 Bimu B4 2
Bentley Historical Library University of Michigan
The records were transferred from the President's Office of the University (donor no. 566 ) and came to the library in 1948. A much smaller portion of materials were accessioned to Shirley W. Smith (donor no. 1718 .)
The collection is open for research.
Since the early part of the twentieth century, the business function of the University of Michigan has undergone several administrative changes. The University's Business Office grew out of the two traditional financial offices: treasurer and secretary. The treasurer's duties "were largely confined to collecting money and making disbursements, whereas the secretary kept the more detailed accounts of receipts and disbursements." The growth of the University in the late nineteenth century, however, spotlighted the deficiencies of this relatively simple system and pointed out the need for more sophisticated accounting methods. The first reorganization occurred in 1909 with the appointment of Shirley W. Smith as Secretary. It was Smith who sought to centralize in the Secretary's office control of the University's financial dealings. In 1914, John C. Christensen came to the University to assist Smith as his Assistant Secretary. In 1927, Smith's title was changed to Secretary and Business manager.
With the appointment of Alexander Ruthven as President in 1929, the University underwent a major reorganization. A carry-over of this occurred in the Secretary's office with the resignation of Treasurer Robert A. Campbell in 1931. The Secretary's office was reorganized into four divisions: accounting, purchasing, cashier, and investments. Smith's title was changed again, this time to Vice-President and Secretary in charge of Business and Finance. John C. Christensen was appointed Controller and Assistant Secretary. The financial management of the University was then centralized in the person of the Vice-President. His responsibilities included the central Business Office, the Department of Buildings and Grounds, and various other departments such as printing and the bindery.)
Smith was secretary from 1908 to 1944. Following his retirement, the office was again revised. Smith's vice-presidential responsibilities were formally separated from his secretarial duties. Robert P. Briggs was named vice-president, while Herbert G. Watkins became secretary. In 1956, because of an illness to Watkins, the secretary's functions were taken over by assistant to the president Erich Walter, who now also became acting secretary. In 1959, the regents formalized the combining of the offices of secretary and assistant to the president. Walter continued in this position until 1966 when he was replaced by Herbert W. Hildebrandt.
Evolution of the Office of Secretary of the University
1909 Shirley W. Smith appointed Secretary
Feb. 1927 Secretary replaced by Secretary and Business Manager (Regents Proceedings)
March 1930 Secretary and Business Manager replaced by Vice- President and Secretary (Regents Proceedings)
Nov. 1944 Vice-President and Secretary replaced in part by Secretary and Assistant Vice-President (Regents Proceedings)
June 1959 Position of Secretary and Assistant Vice-President abolished (Regents Proceedings)
June 1959 Assistant to the President given new title of Secretary of the University and Assistant to the President (Regents Proceedings)
Sept. 1974 Secretary of the University also became Vice-President for State Relations (Regents Proceedings)
Sept. 1985 (State Relations renamed Government Relations)
Sept. 1994 Secretary of the University separated from Vice-President's position (Regents Proceedings)
The records of the University of Michigan Secretary, although including earlier materials from the mid-nineteenth century, are in fact the files of secretary Shirley Wheeler Smith and of controller and assistant secretary John C. Christensen and date primarily from 1908 to 1944.
The secretary was the official who performed much of the detail work involved in the administration of the university. The files of the secretary and of those individuals who worked under him pertain to matters of operations, relations with the state legislature, business and financial dealings, building and grounds, and management of university-wide events (particularly commencements). Within these files, the researcher will also find documentation of the university's struggles during the depression to maintain its facilities and to provide financial aid through employment to deserving students. This information will be found in a topical files series under the headings Federal Emergency Relief Administration and National Youth Administration.
The miscellaneous folders in this record group that fall before the period when Smith was secretary consist of collected materials accumulated by the university's treasurer and pertain to financial dealings of the university (land transactions, bequests, etc.)
Subjects:
Association of University and College Business Officers.; Nichols Arboretum (University of Michigan); University of Michigan. Accounting Office.; University of Michigan--Administration.; University of Michigan--Buildings.; University of Michigan. Business Office.; University of Michigan--Campus.; University of Michigan--Commencements.; University of Michigan. Buildings and Grounds Dept.; University of Michigan--Finance.; University of Michigan--Lands.; University of Michigan. Plant Dept.; University of Michigan. President.; University of Michigan. Treasurer.; University of Michigan. Secretary.; United States. Federal Emergency Relief Administration.; United States. National Youth Administration.
Contributors:
Baker, George Sumner.; Christensen, John Cornelius, 1874-1952.; Smith, Shirley Wheeler, 1875-1959.; Wade, James Henry, 1834-1924.
- Secretary (Shirley W. Smith) Correspondence
  - 1908-1928, 23 folders (Box 1)
  - 1929-1947, 20 folders (Box 2)
- Relations with Legislature 1911-1948
  - 1911-1920 (Box 2)
  - 1923-1935 (Box 3)
  - 1937-1948 (Box 4)
- Commencement files 1910-1946
  - 1910-1916 (Box 4)
  - 1917-1932 (Box 5)
  - 1933-194 1946 (Box 6)
- Office Files
  - Assistant Secretary and Controller (John C. Christensen) files 1913-1944, 11 folders (Box 7)
  - Business Office miscellaneous 1946-1947 (Box 7)
- Topical files
  - Association of University and College Business Officers
    - 1909-1911 1936, 2 folders (Box 7)
    - History written by S.W. Smith, ca. 1936) (Box 7)
  - Auditing Board proceedings 1909-1920, 2 folders; 1 folders (Box 7)
  - Auditor General
    - Reports on U-M funds 1892-1908 (scattered) (Box 7)
    - Special $800,000 appropriation for Defense 1943-1945 (Box 7)
  - Bates (Elizabeth H.) estate 1898-1907 (Box 7)
  - Building Program
    - Building Program history 1927 (Box 8)
    - Organization of the Building Program of the University of Michigan from 1920 to 1926, 2 folders (Box 8)
    - Buildings and Grounds report 1933 (Box 8)
    - Report of Director of Plant Extension relating to building on campus during the depression 1935 (Box 8)
    - Building Program 1945 (Box 8)
    - Horton (R.F.) employment 1925-1926 (Box 8)
  - Buildings
    - Administration Building (proposed) 1933 (Box 8)
    - Betsy Barbour Residence Hall 1919 (Box 8)
    - Central Shops Committee 1919-1923 (Box 8)
    - Dormitory construction 1929, 2 folders (Box 8)
    - East University Avenue Sewer 1923 (Box 8)
    - Gas works, heating, etc. proposals 1877-1879 (Box 8)
    - University Hall 1871-1874 (Box 8)
    - University Hospital 1920 (Box 8)
    - Women's dormitories (planning and financial) 1928-1933, 2 folders (Box 8)
  - Central Shops Committee 1919-1923 (Box 8)
  - Centralized control of business operations 1920-1936 (Box 8)
  - Christensen-Springer disagreement 1923 (Box 8)
  - Civil Works Administration (projects at the University of Michigan) 1934-1937, 2 folders (Box 8)
  - College of Engineering class size 1917 (Box 8)
  - Committee on Budget Administration 1945 (Box 8)
  - Committee on Occupational Deferment 1943-1945 (Box 8)
  - Federal Emergency Relief Administration (federal assistance to students) 1934-1935, 2 folders (Box 8)
  - Forms (accounting and standard letter form) (Box 8)
  - Gifts to U-M, legal status of (correspondence with attorneys) 1913 (Box 8)
  - Land and property transactions 1902 (Box 8)
  - Mail/messenger service at the U-M 1940-1953 (Box 8)
  - National Youth Administration 1935-1943, 4 folders (Box 9)
  - Nichols Arboretum bequest 1922 (Box 9)
  - Preparation of University Operating Budgets 1921-1942 (Box 9)
  - Reports (compiled information) to
    - Bureau of Education, U.S. Dept. of Interior 1911-1919 (Box 9)
    - State Superintendent of Public Instruction 1911-1919 (Box 9)
    - Various (relating to enrollment, faculty, finances 1909-1919 (Box 9)
  - Salary-Wage adjustments 1943-1944 (Box 9)
  - Unit Cost Accounting 1921-1923 (Box 9)
  - University Interest Fund 1845-1864 (Box 9)
  - University Aid from State Treasury 1886 (Box 9)
Related Material
The Bentley Library also has related collections documenting the activities performed by the university secretary. These include (but are not limited to) the personal papers of Shirley Wheeler Smith and John C. Christensen, the records of the business office of the university (cataloged as University of Michigan. Financial Operations), and the papers of individual U-M presidents who worked in close partnership with Smith and Christensen. In addition, for information about similar topics in period following Smith's retirement, the researcher should consult the records of various vice presidents and of the Office of Assistant to the President and Secretary of the University.